<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Some additional remarks on the late book of the Reverend Dean of St. Pauls by a conformable clergy-man.</title>
            <author>Conformable clergy-man.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1681</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 93 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S4471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37573</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">16976003</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 16976003</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105585</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60758)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105585)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1159:24)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Some additional remarks on the late book of the Reverend Dean of St. Pauls by a conformable clergy-man.</title>
                  <author>Conformable clergy-man.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Nathaniel Ranew ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1681.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Stillingfleet, Edward, 1635-1699.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>Leigh Rupinski</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105585:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:105585:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SOME ADDITIONAL REMARKS ON THE LATE BOOK Of the REVEREND DEAN of St. <hi>PA<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>LS.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Conformable Clergy-Man.</p>
            <q>
               <p>Let your moderation be known unto all men, the Lord is at hand,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Phil. 4.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>But if you bite and devour each other, take heed that ye be not conſumed of one another,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gal. 5.15.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Nathaniel Ranew,</hi> at the <hi>Kings Arms</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls-Church-Yard.</hi> 1681.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105585:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105585:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Some Additional Remarques on the late Book of the Reverend Dean of <hi>St. PAULS,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR!</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have read the <hi>Reflections</hi> on the <hi>Preface</hi> to Dr. <hi>Stilling-fleet</hi>'s late Book. You have impoſed another task on me, and that is, to make ſome Remarques alſo on the <hi>Book</hi> it ſelf.</p>
            <p>The Learned Doctor had ſaid in his Sermon, that he dared to ſay, <hi>That if moſt of the Preachers at this day in the ſeparate Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, were ſoberly asked their judgments, Whether it were lawful for the people to join with them in the publick Aſſemblies, they would not deny it.</hi> This Mr. <hi>Alſop</hi> ſays he believes they would flatly deny, and ſpeaks it with confidence. To which the Dr. replies.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I think no man doubts of his confidence that ever looked into his book: but in this matter he is ſo brisk, that he ſaith, he doth not queſtion that he ſhould carry it by the poll; and is withall ſo indiſcreet, as on this occaſion to triumph in the poll of</hi> Nonconformiſts <hi>at</hi> Guildhall, <hi>as though all that gave their votes there, had owned theſe principles of ſeparation; for which many of thoſe Gentlemen will give him little thanks; and is a very unreaſonable boaſting of their numbers.</hi> Page 107.</p>
            <p>This I think is one of the wildeſt concluſions that ever was infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red from any aſſertion. The Dr. had ſaid, that he dared to affirm, that moſt <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> Miniſters would acknowledg (if they were asked) the lawfulneſs of peoples joining in publick Aſſemblies. Mr. <hi>A.</hi> is of another opinion, and believes they (<hi>i.e.</hi> the Nonconform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105585:3"/>Miniſters) would flatly deny it; and ſays he, <hi>Let theſe men be brought to the poll, I queſtion not they will carry it; and I ſuppoſe that though the Dr. preached in the Chappel, he never took the poll of the Nonconformiſts</hi> (<hi>i.e.</hi> the Preachers, in <hi>Guildhall</hi>) The meaning of all which is plainly no more but this: Mr. <hi>A.</hi> believes that more of the Nonconforming Miniſters would deny, than affirm the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs of joining in Parochial Churches; and that if they were numbred, thoſe that are for the negative would carry it. And to rebate the Drs. confidence of the affirmative, he adds, that tho' he preached in the Chappel, yet he never took the poll of the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi> in the Hall, and therefore may be out and miſtaken con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning them.</p>
            <p>How can the Dr. infer from hence, that Mr. <hi>A.</hi> doth indiſcreetly triumph in the number of <hi>Noncon</hi>'s in general, when he ſpake only of their Preachers? How can he infer that Mr. <hi>A.</hi> would ſuggeſt that all that gave their votes there, did own the principles of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration, when he ſpake not one word concerning them? Some men may want perſons to libel and expoſe; but at this rate 'twill be hard to want pretences and occaſions for it; and the Dr. deſerves as little thanks for traducing Mr. <hi>A.</hi> as <hi>he</hi> would have deſerved if he had reported the Gentlemen that gave their Votes at <hi>Guildhall,</hi> as friends to the principles of ſeparation.</p>
            <p>P. 114. The Dr. having diſcourſed the inconvenience of Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon a conceit of purer adminiſtrations, and leſs defective ways of worſhip; and repreſented the ignorance, pride, injudici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, and conceitedneſs of the ordinary ſort of zealous profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors, and the ungovernable and factious humor of that ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the pernicious conſequence of complying with them in the words of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> he enquires, <hi>And muſt the reins be laid on their necks, that they may run whither they pleaſe, becauſe for ſooth they know what is good for their ſouls better than the King doth; and they love their ſouls better than the King doth; and the King cannot bind them to hurt, famiſh, or endanger their ſouls?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Drs. queſtion I ſhall reply, by asking another: Muſt the people be tied neck and heels together, becauſe they are proud, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and injudicious, or becauſe they are inclinable to faction, and ungovernable? Is there no medium betwixt laying the reins up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>neck,</hi> and tying <hi>that</hi> and their heels together? Betwixt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting them a boundleſs liberty, and giving them none at all? Surely methinks 'twere not difficult to ſee an intermediate ſpace be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween extremes ſo vaſtly diſtant from each other.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:105585:3"/>
            <p>And let me add, Do not the people know what Preaching and Preachers do them moſt good? what convinces their judgments, bows their wills, enlivens their affections, and creates upon their ſouls the cleareſt and moſt paſſionate reſolutions for the ſervice of God and their own ſalvation? If they do not know theſe things, they are not men, but brutes. Do not men know which meat and drink doth beſt ſtrengthen and nouriſh, and is leaſt offenſive to their ſtomacks and digeſtive faculties? This I think will be granted: and may they not know what ſort of preaching doth beſt edifie and build them in ſpiritual ſtrength and ſtature? And is it any diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to the King, that the people know theſe things better than he does? Or doth that perſon lay blame upon the King, that ſhould af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm it? And yet this is that which the Doctor ſeems to inſinuate, for he enquires, <hi>Why muſt the King bear all the blame, if mens ſouls be not provided for according to their wiſhes? that is, if they have not ſuch preaching and preachers as they would have.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though the King be not to be blamed, that mens ſouls be no better provided for, there be men in the world that are to be blamed for it, and who they are, let the Doctor conjecture. There are Preachers in this Church that have the <hi>cure of Souls,</hi> to whom an honeſt Country Farmer would ſcarce commit the <hi>care of his Cows.</hi> 'Tis an expreſſion of <hi>Cauſinus.</hi> And who gave theſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſons admiſſion into the ſacred Office, every one knows.</p>
            <p>But the Dr. proceeds, <hi>Doth the King do any thing in this matter, but according to the eſtabliſhed Law and Orders of this Church? why did he not keep to the good old Phraſe of King and Parliament?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is raking into old fores, and looks like a malicious inſinuati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and a deſign of repreſenting Mr. B. as il-loyal, which to ſpeak ſoftly, becomes not the charity and candor of the Doctor. But what if he had kept that good old Phraſe, as he pleaſes to call it, he had done no more than the Doctor himſelf doth in ſenſe, in the lines preceeding, for he ſays, the King <hi>doth nothing but by eſtabliſhed Laws,</hi> and Laws are the Acts of King and Parliament.</p>
            <p>But the Doctor goes on, <hi>And why did he</hi> (<hi>i. e. Mr.</hi> B.) <hi>not put it as it ought to have been, that they know what makes for their own e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification, better than the wiſdom of the whole Nation, aſſembled in Parliament</hi> (i. e. according to the good old Phraſe, the King and Parliament,) <hi>and the Governours of this Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This argument were good, if the wiſdom of the Nation were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, or it were impoſſible they could be miſtaken; but till that
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105585:4"/>be proved, I feel not the weight of it. 'Tis the Popiſh argument, the Doctor knows, and was preſſed againſt the Reformation by the <hi>Romaniſts.</hi> I venerate authority, and am not willing to ſuſpect the wiſdom of it; but I muſt openly profeſs, than I am much more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by the proofs that they make of the wiſdom of their Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, than by their bare Authoritative Aſſertions. I value the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers and Councils, but 'tis not for what they <hi>ſay,</hi> but for what they <hi>prove:</hi> And the like I do ſay of more modern Determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations; and he is a ſtranger in <hi>Hiſtory</hi> as well as <hi>Experience,</hi> that doth not obſerve, that many Laws and Conſtitutions are more the effects of Intereſt, Pride, Paſſion, and Revenge, than of Wiſdom, Juſtice and Righteouſneſs. The Determinations and Conſtitutions of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> are a ſufficient proof hereof, and I wiſh the ſame might not be too truly ſaid of ſome of the more ancient and venarable Councils, yea, and of ſome Laws that are of much later date than the lateſt of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 19th the Doctor quotes theſe words of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> in his Anſwer to his Sermon, <hi>How oft have I told you</hi> (ſaith Mr. <hi>B.</hi>) <hi>that I diſtinguiſh and take thoſe for true Churches that have true Paſtors; but I take thoſe for no true Churches that have</hi> (1.) <hi>Men uncapable of the Paſtoral Office.</hi> (2.) <hi>Or not truly called.</hi> (3.) <hi>Or that deny them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to have the power eſſential to a Paſtor.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">For (ſays the Dr.) one or other of theſe, he thinks moſt, if not all the Parochial Churches in <hi>England,</hi> fall under, and conſequently that the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple may ſeparate from them.</q> That Mr. <hi>B.</hi> doth think ſo, he endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to prove, becauſe if the people judg their Miniſters unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy or incompetent, he allows them liberty to withdraw and ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate.</p>
            <p>'Tis a hard caſe, if people that have an ignorant, drunken, and malignant, ſapleſs Teacher, may not go to the next Congregation, yea or to a <hi>Nonconformiſt</hi> that is a man of better abilities, and a bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter converſation, without being reputed Schiſmaticks; and methinks no man of p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ety, and that knows how much mens graces and virtues are actuated by ſerious, lively, and vigorous preaching, and how they languiſh and dwindle under that which is dry, trifling, luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm and unſerious ſhould doubt of it.</p>
            <p>But ſai h the Dr. p. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>2. <q rend="margQuotes">God (ſaith Mr. <hi>B.</hi>) in nature and Scriptu e hath given the people that conſenting power, antece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to the Prince's, which none can take from them.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:105585:4"/>
            <p>I cannot tell how to believe that God hath given any Prince or Governour of Churches a greater power over their people than Parents have over their children in the choice of Employments, or diſpoſals in Marriage. A Father may propoſe an Employment or Match to his Son or Daughter, but he may not impoſe them againſt their own conſent, as is generally acknowledged. Again, if in ſuch caſes they chuſe amiſs, and to their apparent danger, they may for bid them; and thus much Magiſtrates may and ought to do; but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they may impoſe againſt the conſent of the people, ſeems to me not ſo clear as ſome men imagine. And this is all that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> deſires, which might be granted, and the right of Patrons preſerved too, for ought that I can ſee.</p>
            <p>But the Dr. adds, <hi>ibid.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">Mr. <hi>B.</hi> makes the people judg of the worthineſs and competency of their Miniſters, in caſe incompe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent Miniſters be ſet over the people, though it be half the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes in a Kingdom, or only the tenth part, it is no Schiſm, ſaith he, but a duty, for thoſe that are deſtitute, to chuſe thoſe that they judg moſt competent; and 'tis a duty for faithful Miniſters, though forbidden by Superiors, to perform their Office to ſuch people that deſire it.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Let me beg leave to ask the Reverend Dr. whether there can be ſuch a thing as an incompetent Paſtor ſet over a people? If he grants it, as ſure he cannot deny it, I would ask him again, what the people muſt do in ſuch a caſe? if he ſays, they muſt complain, and uſe regular ways for his removal; I would again enquire, what if they be poor, and not able to bear the charge of ſuch a proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing? or if after all endeavours, they cannot remove him (and I will aſſure him, 'tis no eaſie matter to remove an incompetent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor) what muſt they do? muſt they ſtarve at home, or be treat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as Separatiſts, if they go abroad to hear a Diſſenter that Preaches in the Neighbourhood? If it be ſaid, that the people are no capable judges of a Miniſters abilities; and ſo the Dr. intimates in ſeveral places of his Book (page 123, 124. <hi>&amp; paſſim</hi>). I anſwer, the Learned Dr. allows Separation, and thinks it duty too in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain caſes, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">1. In caſe of Idolatrous worſhip. 2. In caſe of falſe Doctrine, impoſed inſtead of true. And 3. In caſe things indifferent be made neceſſary to ſalvation, page 213.214.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I deſire to learn from this worthy Dr. whether the people in theſe caſes are bound to ſeparate? or whether the obligation lies only on the Paſtors? if it lyes on both (and on both it muſt lie, or elſe the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105585:5"/>people are bound to be damned) then the people muſt judg, and if they may judg in theſe caſes, I know not why they may not make a judgment of the competency of their Miniſters. He is an incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Paſtor that Preaches falſe Doctrine or Hereſie, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends and practiſes Idolatry, and makes things indifferent neceſſary to ſalvation; and in theſe the people may judg by the Doctors own confeſſion; and if they may judg in theſe, they may judg in ſome other caſes, for ought that I can perceive.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I am not about to deny that the people, at leaſt of them, are ignorant injudicious, and raſh; and do many times cenſure and condemn the innocent and worthy. All that I deſign is to make it a little evident, that there is a mean betwixt the two ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes, and that ſhould be enquired after. The people are neither the wiſeſt among men, nor are they a herd of beaſts. In ſome things they may and muſt judg, in others it may be denied them.</p>
            <p>But the Dr. proceeds (p. 123.) and ſays, <q rend="margQuotes">Mr. <hi>B.</hi> bids the people not think that he is perſuading them to make no difference, but after he hath ſet aſide the utterly inſufficient and heretical (of which the people are admirable Judges) he lays down this gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral rule, Any one whoſe Miniſtry is ſuch as tendeth more to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction than edification, is not to be owned, and conſequently to be ſeparated from.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in good earneſt, is no difference to be made of Miniſters? then farewell all lawful as well as unlawful Separation. The peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple are not Judges of Inſufficiency or Hereſie, and therefore muſt ſwallow all that they propound, and go along with their Paſtors to the Devil; and though they preach more for the encouragement of ſin and vice, than they do for godlineſs and virtue, yet the people muſt not ſeparate from them. This, to ſpeak modeſtly, is ſomething crudely ſpoken, and not with that uſual judgment and caution as the Dr. expreſſes (or ſhould expreſs) his ſentiments.</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">But the Dr. ſays, this is directly contrary to the principles of the old <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> and even to Mr. <hi>B.</hi> himſelf: for as a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuiſt (ſays he, p. 124.) he thus determines, 1. <hi>That a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters perſonal faults do not allow people to ſeparate from the Worſhip of God.</hi> 2. <hi>Nor ull Miniſterial faults, but only thoſe that prove him or his Miniſtration utterly intollerable.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Well, and where is the inconſiſtency of this determination with what the Dr. quoted from him in the page before? Did he there ſay that every perſonal or Miniſterial fault would juſtifie Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105585:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>I can find no ſuch thing, he only mentions the utterly inſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient and heritical, ſuch as do more hurt than good; and I think theſe are the ſame with ſuch as prove Miniſters, and their Miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion utterly intollerable. But by this, and many other paſſages in this Book, a man would be tempted to think, that ſome others write in haſte, and without the advice of their friends, as well as Mr. <hi>B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 130. The Dr. ſays, that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> makes Conformity it ſelf a ſcandalous thing, and then tells the people over and over, <q rend="margQuotes">it is no ſin to ſeparate from ſcandalous Prieſts, eſpecially when the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal is notorious, as it is in this caſe. And <hi>Page</hi> 131. the Dr. adds, He chargeth us with down-right Lying, and Perjury, and tells me of Thirty tremendous aggravations of the ſin of Conformity, among which are Lying, and Perjury, and drawing on our ſelves the guilt of many thouſand Perjuries.</q>
            </p>
            <p>To this I anſwer in Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s own words of his firſt Plea in the Preface, <hi>I write not this</hi> (ſays he) <hi>as accuſing Conformiſts, or the Law-makers, but as anſwering their long and loud accuſations and demands; and if telling what I fear, ſeem a telling what others are guilty of, it is a conſequent which I cannot avoid.</hi> In his ſecond Plea, having aſſerted the moral impoſſibility of bringing all good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians to believe Conformity lawful, he gives many reaſons for it, and among others this, becauſe Conformity looks like a horrid and frightful evil, being no leſs than deliberate Lying, and Perjury, and the juſtifying of thouſands in it, and the publick renouncing en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours of Reformation. And then he adds, <hi>I am not ſaying, that all theſe, or any of them are ſuch as they fear them to be, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that they fear them to be ſuch,</hi> pag. 173. And in his Anſwer to the Drs. Sermon, theſe are his words, <hi>I have only told you how many, and heinous the ſins are which we fear we ſhould be guilty of, ſhould we Conform,</hi> pag. 52. Hence 'tis obvious enough by Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s. words, that he accuſes not others, but vindicates himſelf and his brethren from the imputation of keeping up a Schiſm againſt their own conſciences; and in that very Chapter, where he reckons up the ſeveral agravations of Perjury and Lying, he doth not deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine, that the Conformable Clergy are guilty of them, but ſays, <hi>If they be ſo, ſuch are the aggravations of their ſin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, I pray, let it be impartially conſidered, whether Mr <hi>B.</hi> hath not a difficult province to manage. If he gives no reaſon or
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105585:6"/>account of his own, and his brethrens Nonconformity, he and they are unconſcionable Schiſmaticks; if he do give ſome reaſon for it, and account of it, then he is interpreted to accuſe the Conformiſts, and repute them ſcandalous, and perſwade the people to Separation, though he renounced all ſuch accuſations, as is obvious from his words before-mentioned.</p>
            <p>Yet after all this I have ſaid on the behalf of this reverend man, I muſt add (for I am my ſelf a Conformiſt) that I am not of his opinion in the interpretation of the Subſcriptions, and Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations impoſed on the Clergy. They are of ambiguous ſenſe and meaning; for what the ſenſe of the Law makers and Impoſers is, who can be ſure? I cannot tell; and if you enquire, ſome will ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly refuſe to give any ſenſe or meaning of them; others will expound them, ſome in one ſenſe, and ſome in another. The caſe being thus, I do not think my ſelf obliged to underſtand them in the worſt ſenſe that can be put opon them, but in a ſenſe of favour: and ſuch a ſenſe (Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſays) is by the moſt judicious Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts put on them, that he and his brethren themſelves would ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit to them, if they could believe <hi>that</hi> were indeed the meaning of them. I am not ſatisfied as yet, that I am obliged to underſtand them in any other; which I ſpeak in vindicatinn of my own and my brethrens Conformity, without reflection on thoſe of other ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions, or juſtifying the Impoſitions. And upon this ſcore there is a Paper Printed the laſt year <hi>as an account of the</hi> London <hi>Sheriffs holding their Office,</hi> Which, if any man doth honeſtly fear God, ſo as he <hi>would</hi> in good earneſt Conform if he <hi>could,</hi> but <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not</hi> in point of ſcruple, I would commend to his peruſal: who may perhaps ſee more to ſatisfy him in that one (but very <hi>full,</hi> and very <hi>much conſidered</hi>) ſingle ſheet, in regard to our preſent Conformity, than he hath found hitherto in other Books upon that Subject, though there be many which are, or which would make Volumes, that are written.</p>
            <p>In Page 132. the Dr. charges Mr. <hi>B.</hi> with ſaying, that he over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throws all Religion, and ſets up man in rebellion againſt God. To which I anſwer, all that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> intends in thoſe words, is no more but thus, Such is the conſequence of the Drs. Doctrine. Whether it be rightly inferred, let the Dr. and Mr. <hi>B.</hi> determine. But this I am ſure of, that the Dr. infers many things from Mr. <hi>b</hi>'s. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which he deteſts and abhors, as truly as himſelf abhors the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up man above God. Such are all <hi>Principles inconſiſtent with Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:105585:6"/>and all <hi>Pleas</hi> which lay the <hi>foundation for diſorder and confuſion,</hi> whatſoever he ſays, page 137. and 139.</p>
            <p>The Dr. had ſaid in the <hi>Preface</hi> to his Sermon, <q>If it be lawful to ſeparate on the pretence of greater purity, where there is an agreement in Doctrine, and the ſubſtantial parts of Worſhip, as is acknowledged in our caſe, then a bare difference of opinion, as to ſome circumſtances of Worſhip, in the beſt Conſtitution of Churches, will be ground ſufficient for Separation; and this, conſidering the variety of mens fancies, is to make an infinite di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibility in Churches.</q> To which Mr. <hi>A.</hi> makes this reply, <hi>That though ſome petty and inconſidrrable inconveniencies, ſome litlte trouble, may ariſe to a Church from the levity and volubility of mens minds, yet this is no reaſon why they ſhould enſlave their judgments and conſciences to others.</hi> So the Dr. quotes him, but he expreſſes himſelf more at large, and with words of greater weight, as may be ſeen in his <hi>Preface.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From theſe words of Mr. <hi>A.</hi> the Dr. takes occaſion to enquire, <q>what a rare advocate had this man been for the <hi>Novatians, Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Luciferians,</hi> or whatſoever Schiſmaticks rent the Church in pieces in former times.</q> And ſuppoſing St. <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> and other great oppoſers of the ancient Schiſms, to be met to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: he gathers from theſe words, and the Principles of Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that he lays down elſewhere in his <hi>Books,</hi> how he would accoſt them. Page 198, Then forms an elegant Oration for him, ſuppoſing him haranguing it before them. Page 198, 199. And page 200. theſe expreſſions he puts in his mouth. <q>Why do you <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Cyprian,</hi> and other Reverend Fathers, cry out ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten of the Sacrilegiouſneſs of Schiſm? We know no other Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg, but the Sacrilegious deſertion of our Miniſtry in obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to the Laws; this is a Sacriledg we often talk of, and tell the people it is far worſe than robbing Church-plate, conſidering what precious gifts we have.</q>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe laſt words are, I am afraid, a prophane jeer, and look more like words dropt from the pen of <hi>Ben. Johnſon,</hi> or <hi>Fletcher,</hi> than that of Dr. <hi>St.</hi> Hath not God endued Mr. <hi>B.</hi> (for 'tis on him he reflects) and other <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> with <hi>precious gifts</hi> (for 'tis a Scripture-word, and I'le make bold to uſe it, though I be thought to cant)? and can the Dr. deny it? or doth it become his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity to deride them? If he muſt uſe his Sarcaſtick faculty, I wiſh he would chuſe ſome common objects to employ it on, and not on
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105585:7"/>things that are ſacred and divine; for ſuch are the gifts wherewith Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and others of his Brethren are bleſſed of God; and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the Dr. in his conſcience can't deny it, however he takes li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to deride them.</p>
            <p>And when, I pray, and where did Mr. <hi>B.</hi> or any of his brethren ſay, they knew no Sacriledg but that of the Sacrilegious deſertion of their Miniſtry? Let this be proved, or elſe it muſt be reputed a defamation. But peradventure the Dr. will ſay, That when men play the Orator, they are not obliged to ſpeak exact truth; but where will he find any thing in Scripture to patroniz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it? He en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to juſtifie an ugly ſarcaſm that he made uſe of in his S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, by theſe words of our Saviour, <hi>I came not to call the righteous, but ſinners to repentance;</hi> but I am not very certain they will ſerve his purpoſe; for ſome men that the Dr. values, as well as ſome that he deſpiſes, give another interpretation of them, as he very well knows; but where he will find any to juſtifie this Catechreſtical ſcoff, I cannot tell: but may be he may <hi>find,</hi> or <hi>make</hi> one do it.</p>
            <p>But why doth the Dr. add, <hi>in obedience to the Laws?</hi> Do all Laws oblige ſo far, as for Miniſters upon that account to deſert their Office? If ſo, then may not only the three children go to the fiery Furnace, and <hi>Daniel</hi> to the Lyons, but all Proteſtant Preachers to the flames, if they continue to exerciſe their Miniſtry againſt the prohibition of Popiſh Laws? If not, then 'tis not Laws, but the equity and juſtice of Laws, that lays an obligation on them; and that is the controverſie between him and his Nonconformable Brethren, in which I will not interpoſe. But this is not the only place where the weight of the Drs. Arguments is little for want of diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, reſtriction, and limitation. And this is an infirmity and weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of diſcourſe, that runs through a great part of his Book, and which renders it invalid to his Adverſaries, and eſpecially Mr. <hi>B.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But the Dr. enquires, <hi>Whether it be not a ſin to break the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches Communion?</hi> p. 198. To which I anſwer, Yes doubtleſs, all unneceſſary Separation is a ſin, and ſuch I do eſteem much of the preſent Separation in <hi>England.</hi> But what then? Are all that are Schiſmatical, unworthy to live upon the earth? Muſt they be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted by Laws to Impriſonment, Baniſhment, and Death? Is there no way of curing a wound in the arm or leg, but by amputation? Are not Drunkenneſs, Adultery, Lying, and Swearing, ſins? Yes ſurely, 'twill not be denied. But muſt all theſe Criminals be injured, proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:105585:7"/>and ſent to the <hi>Indies?</hi> This would be thought unreaſonable. And why perſons of ſome Schiſmatical Principles (provided the main of their doctrine be ſound, and conſiſtent with Chriſtianity) may not have as much favour as drunkards and other immoral men, I know not.</p>
            <p>But are there no other ways of reforming the Schiſmatical bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mors of men, but Gaols and Confiſcations, and other like Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? Are there no methods of reclaiming Schiſmaticks, but by Rods and Axes? Are not perſonal inſtructions and kindneſs more agreeable to the nature of the Paſtoral Office, and the ſpirit of our Saviour, whoſe ſervants we are, and whoſe work we are to do in the world? Methinks no man that hath read the New Teſtament, ſhould doubt of it; and I do confeſs that I hate theſe Military me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of converting Diſſenters, and I never ſaw any good come of them.</p>
            <p>I live in a Town where there are ſome Diſſenters; I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways treated them with kindneſs, and have avoided to exaſperate them either in my publick or private diſcourſes; and by this means they will come ſometimes to hear me, and will grant me to be a Miniſter of Jeſus Chriſt; whereas had I railed at them, or proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted them at Law, or encouraged others to do it, they would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver have come at me, but accounted me a Limb of Antichriſt, and a Factor or Agent for the Devil. And I muſt and do openly avow, that 'tis more eaſie to my mind to think, that when they are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent from my Congregation, they are ſerving God elſewhere, than it would be to think they were ſome of them in priſons, their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies wanting bread, and others crying to God for vengeance on me as a perſecutor; and which is moſt eaſie to my mind <hi>living,</hi> I doubt not will be ſo <hi>dying.</hi> They are perſons of holy lives and upright converſations, at leaſt ſome of them; and I would not have a hand in perſecuting and undoing them, for all the Preferments this Church or this World affords.</p>
            <p>Let me add thus much on the behalf of Mr. <hi>A.</hi> I do not believe that he either deſires or pleads for univerſal Toleration, or would defend all the ancient Schiſmaticks, or that he would open his mouth on the behalf of <hi>Socinians, Arrians, Anti-Trinitarians, Quakers,</hi> or other like Sectarian Infidels: all that he pleads for, is liberty for peaceable and Chriſtian Diſſenters; but I do think that the Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>end Dr. hath wrung from his words ſuch a ſenſe as he never intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or did once enter into his thoughts.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:105585:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Pag.</hi> 273. The Dr. ſays, <q>I do not ſee but the objections made againſt the Diſcipline of this Church, might be removed, if the things allowed and required by the Rules thereof (that is, Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of children by the Biſhop, when they are able to give an account of the neceſſary points of Chriſtian faith and practice, and Certificate be made thereof by the Miniſter of the Pariſh) were duly practiſed, and might attain to as great purity as is ever pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended to by the ſeparate Congregations, who now find ſo much fault for our want of diſcipline.</q>
            </p>
            <p>I wiſh with all my heart the Rules of the Church were reduced to practice, which I am ſure they never can nor will be, whilſt the Dioceſſes in <hi>England</hi> are of the preſent dimenſions. He that thinks any Biſhop can confirm all the children in his Dioceſs, doth but dream: were he never ſo deſirous of it, and diligent in it, 'twere impracticable; and the neglect and impracticableneſs of this thing, is one great reaſon of the ignorance and wickedneſs of our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes and Congregations; and thus 'tis like to be, till Dioceſſes be leſſened and the number of Biſhops encreaſed, and ſome effectual care taken that children be inſtructed and confirmed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 275. The Dr. aſſerts a power in the Presbyters of this Church to reject and deny the holy Sacrament to the ſcandalouſly wicked, provided he give notice of it to the Ordinary within four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days; and for this produces the Rubrick before the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion.</p>
            <p>I grant what the Rubrick allows: but is not the Miniſter like to have a ſine time of it, if he muſt be bound to inform and proſecute all at Law that are ſcandalous and unfit to come to the holy Table? The Dr. knows that all above the age of ſixteen are bound to take the Sacrament three times a year by the Orders of this Church; and in ſome great Pariſhes the number of the ſcandalous and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed is ſo great, that if the Miniſter be bound to proſecute all whom he accounts himſelf obliged in conſcience to refuſe, the life of a Ken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nel-raker were more elegible than his; for he muſt ſpend his time in perpetual travel and attendance upon Courts, which is a very ſine Employment for a man of piety and conſcience, and that deſires to ſpend his time in his ſtudy, and teaching and inſtructing the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple committed to his care.</p>
            <p>But the Dr. enquires <hi>What, would you have every particular Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor have an unaccountable power? Or would you not have them bound to juſtifie what they do, and proſecute the perſon for thoſe faults for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105585:8"/>which they exclude him from the Communion?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, 1. I think it were not amiſs, if the excluded perſon were obliged to complain if he thought himſelf wronged, and the Miniſters were excuſed from doing the Office of an Apparitor; but this I inſiſt not on. Therefore I add, I plead not for an unaccounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble power in particular Paſtors, but for ſuch a power as they may account for; which I am ſure they can never do for <hi>this</hi> in great pariſhes, and where the Dioceſſes are ſo large and wide; and there is no man that will give himſelf the liberty to think, can deny it. The number of the ſcandalous is ſo great, the diſtance from the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Court in many places ſo far, the tediouſneſs and corruption of the Officers ſo abominable, that it is a thing utterly impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable. 'Tis impoſſible that any man can juſtifie himſelf in refuſing to proſecute according to Canon all the ſcandalous that he may juſtly reject. In brief, either to talk or think of exerciſing Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, or reforming this Church, till we have more Biſhops or Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragans, and other things altered (which might be done if our Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors pleaſed, without altering the Conſtitution) is to build Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles in the air, and to dream of Rocks to ſet them on, among the clouds of heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 278. The Dr. quotes theſe words of Mr. <hi>B. If a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter doth publickly admoniſh a perſon by name, not cenſured by the Ordinary, the Lawyers tell him he may have his Action againſt him.</hi> To which he replies: <q>What need this publick admonition? Doth the nature of Church-diſcipline lye in that?</q>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer: No man ever dreamt that the whole na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of Church-diſcipline conſiſted in publick admonition by name. There are ſeveral intermediate acts of Diſcipline; Publick admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition by name is not to be attempted till others have been eſſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and tryed in vain. And this publick admonition (after the fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs uſe of that which is private) is that which Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſays can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not legally be performed by the Presbyters of this Church.</p>
            <p>But the Dr. makes a ſecond Reply to thoſe words of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> 
               <q>If a reſtraint be laid on Miniſters by Law, the queſtion then comes to this, Whether the obligation to admoniſh publickly an offender, or to deny him the Sacrament if he will come to it, be ſo great, as to bear him out in the violation of a Law made by publick Authority, with a deſign to preſerve our Religion?</q>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, I do not think that Miniſters are obliged to admoniſh publickly all offenders after the unſucceſsful tryal of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105585:9"/>means and endeavours, though no Law forbad it. Pearls are not to be caſt before Swine. If the perſon or perſons be ſuch as will miſchief, wound, or kill the Miniſter that ſhould ſo admoniſh him or them, I think he is not obliged to do it: but whether out of that caſe, and others of like nature, a Miniſter may not be obliged to do it, is another queſtion, yea, though the Law ſhould forbid it. And 'tis another queſtion, whether he be obliged to give ſuch a perſon the holy Sacrament, though the Law ſhould command it: Mans Laws are not valid againſt Gods. If God obliges Miniſters to publick admonition of ſcandalous and incorrigible offenders, and to refuſe them a participation in the holy myſteries of our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, no man can take off the obligation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 281. The Dr. ſays, <q>The due exerciſe of diſcipline is a work of ſo much prudence and difficulty, that the greateſt Zealots for it have not thought it fit to be truſted in the hands of every Parochial Miniſter, and his particular Congregation, and for this he quotes <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer: I believe there are very few Pariſh-prieſts in <hi>England</hi> that are ambitious of having the exerciſe of diſcipline committed to their care and conduct; and indeed very many of them have neither piety or prudence ſufficient for the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of it. But withall I muſt add, I ſhould be very ſorry (and ſome are very worthy of blame if it be ſo) if moſt Pariſh-Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters be not as capable of it as Chancellors, Commiſſaries. Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, and Surrogates, who are the people that exerciſe what Diſcipline is exerciſed in this Church; and 'tis ſufficiently known, that many of them are perſons of none of the greateſt underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, the beſt prudence, the tendereſt conſciences, or the ſevereſt lives, which yet are qualifications, hugely neceſſary in perſons that manage the Diſcipline of the Church.</p>
            <p>In brief, I condemn not the prudence of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in not committing the <hi>exerciſe</hi> of Diſcipline to every Pariſh-Miniſter; but then I would humbly move, that we might have Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops enough to do it. The Dr. appropriates to Biſhops, Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, Ordination, and Cenſures, and I am very well content they have them, provided they will, or can diſcharge them. But of the impoſſibility of that, I am paſt doubt; for though the Dioceſſes of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Biſhops be not ſo great as that of the Pope (which the Dr. acknowledges to be too great and ſpacious) yet I think they are too large for their management, and that the duty incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:105585:9"/>on them, with reſpect unto them, is utterly impracticable. <hi>Mount Athos, Polion,</hi> or <hi>Oſſa,</hi> are neither of them ſo great as the Globe of the earth, yet they are all burthens utterly inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table.</p>
            <p>Whether the Dr. will allow this multiplication of Biſhops (or Suffragans rather, that the name Biſhop may not become too com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, and ſo become leſs venerable), I cannot tell. I find him in many places of his <hi>Book,</hi> and in his <hi>Preface,</hi> very jealous <hi>of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of our Reformation,</hi> and poſitively reſolved, never to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn the Conſtitution of this Church, nor the lawfulneſs of the Ceremonies hitherunto practiſed in it, <hi>vide Pref. p.</hi> 89.</p>
            <p>I have my ſelf a very great eſteem for the Reformation of this Church, and a mighty honour for the great and incomparable <hi>Hero's,</hi> that were the Reformers of it; but 'tis no diſparagement to ſay, they were but men (though the greateſt men); nor is it any Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the Reformation to ſay, it was imperfect, The Learned and Pious Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi> hath obſerved divers defects, and imperfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in it (and I know not how they can be denied); and to ſpeak the truth concerning it, is not to reproach it. And what if it ſhould be ſaid, that among others 'twas an imperfection in our Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that the number of Biſhops was not increaſed ſo far, as that they might be ſufficient for the work and duty incumbent on them? Can a Biſhop inſpect the Clergy in a Dioceſs of the preſent dimen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? can he exerciſe the Cenſures of the Church upon all the cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable delinquents in it? can he confirm all the Children in it? can he ordain Prieſts for all the Pariſhes therein, with that circumſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, warineſs, and care, which was obſerved by the primitive Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and which the honour of this Church, the Chriſtian Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the ſalvation of ſouls doth require? Doth the Reverend Dr. think thoſe things can be done by any, the moſt diligent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious Biſhop on earth? I dare ſay, he cannot think it poſſible; and if he doth not think it poſſible, I would enquire further of him, whether he does not think it very neceſſary and deſirable, that all this work were put into more hands, that they may be capable of performing it? for till then, I am much aſſured it can never be done, however neceſſary or deſirable it may be?</p>
            <p>Theſe things being ſaid, I will now add, I ſhall never deſire the Dr. to condemn the Conſtitution of this Church (nor will I brlieve many of the Nonconformiſts deſire him to do it), but I would hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly deſire him, to put to his helping hand, for the amendment and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105585:10"/>perfecting of it; and to perfect and compleat it, is not to condemn it; 'tis only to confeſs it a little ſhort of that perfection that it may attain; and what great work is perfect of a ſudden, at its birth into the world? In brief, Dioceſan Epiſcopacy I like (and that's the Conſtitution of this Church), and ſo doth Mr. <hi>B.</hi> for ought that I can ſee: but I would fain have more Biſhops, not to <hi>controul Epiſcopal Power,</hi> but to aſſiſt in the performance of Epiſcopal Duty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 301. The Dr. undertakes to confute what Mr. <hi>B.</hi> had ſaid, <hi>(viz.)</hi> that wherever there is the true notion of a Church, there muſt be a conſtitutive regent part (<hi>i. e.</hi> a ſtanding governing pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er) which is an eſſential part of it, and this he promiſes to do from Mr. <hi>B.</hi> himſelf.</p>
            <p>How well he hath done it, let the Reader judg, by what the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor of the <hi>Peaceable Deſign</hi> hath replied to him upon this Subject. But the Dr. infers from what Mr. <hi>B.</hi> had ſaid of the neceſſity of a Regent Head to every Church, as followeth:</p>
            <p>
               <q rend="margQuotes">And ſo Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s. Conſtitutive Regent part of a Church, hath done the Pope a wonderful kindneſs, and made a very plauſible plea for his univerſal Paſtorſhip. But there are ſome men in the world, who do not attend to the advantages they give to Popery, ſo they may vent their ſpleen againſt the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, Mr. <hi>B</hi>'s Conſtitutive Regent part of a Church, hath done the Pope no kindneſs at all; for another viſible Head may be aſſigned to the Catholick Church, and that is the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Jeſus; he is both the viſible and inviſible Head thereof; he is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it both a Head of government, and a Head of influence; he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verns it by his Laws, and by the influence of his Spirit, and hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed inferiour officers for the government and direction of it, according to his own inſtitutions: and though he be not ſeen by mortals here below, yet he is viſible, and that is enough to conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute him the viſible Head of the Catholick viſible Church. There are ſome Kingdoms that never ſee their Prince, and in all King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, multitudes of Subjects that never lay their eyes on him, and yet he is never the leſs their Civil viſible Head.</p>
            <p>But there are ſome men in the world, that will take very ſmall occaſions to ſignifie their diſpleaſure againſt Mr. <hi>B.</hi> and what hath he done to deſerve their laſh? and why muſt he be the Subject of theſe moſt twinging Satyrs? they are the words of a late Author: and what is the ſpleen that he vents againſt the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:105585:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>that makes their choler to ferment and boyl?</p>
            <p>'Tis true, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> doth, with a brave and generous courage, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buke what he thinks amiſs in the gnvernours and government of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> he ſpeaks plainly, and without reſpect of perſons; he flatters none, nor fawns upon none, but indifferently reproves whatever he thinks worthy of it, in whomſoever it be. And if this be to vent his ſpleen againſt the Church of <hi>England,</hi> I think he hath very venerable patterns and examples for it, both in the Old Teſtament and the New, as this Learned Dr. very well knows.</p>
            <p>If it ſhould be ſaid, that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> reproves where there is no fault, I anſwer, I ſhould much rejoice if this were true, and I believe ſo would Mr. <hi>B.</hi> as well as I: but he muſt ſhut his eyes againſt the mid-day light, that thinks there is no fault in the Government of this Church, or nothing worthy of the plaineſt and moſt keen re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofs therein. 'Twere very eaſie to name many things, if a man delighted to rake in Sinks and Kennels, I mean, the proceedings in the Spiritual Courts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Page</hi> 302. The Dr. tells us, that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> had ſaid in his Anſwer to his Sermon, that he would fain learn of him, what thoſe rules and ties are which make a National Church, whether divine or humane? If it be a divine rule, we (ſays Mr. <hi>B.</hi>) are of the National Church as well as you; if humane, he enquires how conſent in theſe makes a National Church? and how they come to be of the National Church which do not conſent in them? and objects the differences among the Conformable Clergy, in the expoſition of ſome of the Articles of this Church.</p>
            <p>To which the Dr. anſwers three things. I ſhall take notice only of the laſt of them, <hi>(viz.)</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">There is no difference among us con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the lawfulneſs of the orders of our Church, and duty of ſubmiſſion to them; if there be any other differences, they are not material<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and I believe, are no other than in the manner of explaining ſome things which may happen in the beſt ſociety in the world, without breaking the peace of it; as about the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference of orders, the ſenſe of ſome paſſages in the Athanaſian Creed, the true explication of one or two Articles, which are the things he (<hi>i. e.</hi> Mr. <hi>B.</hi>) mentions. A multitude of ſuch diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences will never overthrow ſuch a conſent among us, as to make us not to be members of the ſame National Church.</q>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:105585:11"/>
            <p>To the firſt lines of this Paragraph, which concern the agreement of the Members of this Church in the lawfulneſs of its orders, and the duty of ſubmiſſion to them, I ſhall reply nothing. To the reſt I ſay, I am perfectly of the Dr's. opinion; and were it reduced to practice, it would heal the moſt of the diviſions, and put a period to moſt of the ſeparations that have rent and torn this Church in pieces for many years. Why might not the Diſſenters among us have been permitted to have continued in the Miniſtry, and in the Church, though they differed in ſome things in their judgments from the Conformable Clergy? Would it have broken the peace thereof, any more than the various apprehenſions that are at preſent among themſelves? They are not all of a mind in the five points; ſome of them underſtand and believe them after the ſenſe of <hi>Calvin,</hi> and others after the ſenſe of <hi>Arminius;</hi> and I might mention ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others wherein they differ among themſelves, but the thing is ſufficiently known, and there is no need of it: And are the diffe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rences among the Conformiſts themſelves reconcilable with peace; and thoſe wherein the Nonconformiſts differ from them (though they be no greater than the other) irreconcilable with it? What ſtrange partiality is this? Conformiſts may differ in multitudes of things, without breaking the peace of the Church; but if thoſe that are Diſſenters, differ from them in a few impertinent and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, things, the peace of the Church is ſubverted, and all things put into confuſion thereby. The Conformiſts doubt (at leaſt ſome of them) whether Biſhops and Presbyters do differ in <hi>order</hi> or in <hi>degree,</hi> ſome are paſt all doubt concerning it, and do affirm they differ in <hi>order</hi> and not barely in <hi>degree.</hi> This breaks no peace<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The Nonconformiſts cannot find that Word of God, whereby 'tis cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that children indefinitely) which are baptized, dying before they commit actual ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, are undoubtedly ſaved: and they are not very ſure, that all children that are baptized, are <hi>regenerate by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>irit,</hi> or that they may ſafely ſay of all that they bury, that <hi>God of his great mercy hath taken to himſelf the ſoul</hi> of the deceaſed per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and give him <hi>hearty thanks</hi> that it hath pleaſed him to <hi>deliver him out of the afflictions of this ſinful world:</hi> and theſe are ſuch dreadful and formidable things, that the Church cannot be ſafe, if the Members, or at leaſt any of the Preachers in it, diſpute the truth of them, and therefore out they muſt go; and if they at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to exerciſe their Miniſterial Office after they are ejected, they are immediately the moſt damnable Schiſmaticks that ever
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:105585:11"/>the world did know, and Priſons, Fines, Confiſcations, Baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and all that is evil, is beneath their ſin and trangreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>Why a difference of opinion in theſe things might not be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with peace, as well as in others that are of as great, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what greater import (at leaſt in my apprehenſion) I am not able to divine; if nothing but Reaſon and Religion were to determine concerning them: but if ſpight, malice, and revenge, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of thoſe Antichriſtian paſſions, be called to counſel, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to judg of them, 'tis not difficult to give a reaſon of the dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering natures of theſe differences, why ſome are judged conſiſtent with peace, and others utterly inconſiſtent with it. But enough of this paragraph. I ſhall conclude with one ſupplication to all the Conformable Clergy in <hi>England</hi> on the behalf of the Diſſenters; and 'tis this, That they may be permitted to differ from them in things of no greater moment than thoſe in which they differ among themſelves. If it be ſaid, 'tis not in their power to permit it: I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, Time was when it was very much in their power to have done it; and I think they might do well to uſe ſome endeavours to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve it; or at leaſt give ſome evidence that they wiſh well to it. This I think is no unreaſonable requeſt; how it may be reſented, I know not; 'tis the love of this Church, and the peace thereof, that hath cauſed me to propoſe it, and that ſhall ſatisfie my mind.</p>
            <p>But having ſaid this on the behalf of the Diſſenters, I muſt add a word or two on my own behalf, and that is, That a fair and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable ſenſe may be, and is put upon theſe paſſages mentioned from the <hi>Rubrick</hi> and <hi>Liturgy,</hi> by the Conformable Clergy, and amongſt them by my ſelf; but what is that to thoſe whoſe judgments and conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences will not permit them to put that ſenſe upon them? All mens minds are not caſt in the ſame mould; all cannot admit that lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of ſenſe, and expoſition in thoſe and many other things, that ſome men do and can without offence and neglect to their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; and muſt they therefore be ſhut out of the Vineyard of the Lord, and denied the liberty of working there? Certainly this is a ſevere method of proceeding, and hardly reconcilable with the Laws of Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>The Learned Dr. in ſeveral places of his Book repreſents Mr. <hi>A.</hi> as unlearned, unread, and very weak in his reafoning and argumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations. Page 174. <hi>he accuſes him of childiſh trifling about</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a <hi>Canon;</hi> and in the ſame page, and that next to it, he miſlikes his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105585:12"/>of the words <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, leaving out <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which he obſerves from <hi>Grotius</hi> is not found in one Manuſcript, the ſenſe whereof he thus expreſſes; <hi>What we have attained, let us walk up to the ſame;</hi> and that <hi>Greek</hi> phraſe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which he ſays <hi>implies no more than minding that very thing, viz.</hi> v. 14. <hi>preſſing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the mark:</hi> and then adds; <hi>But if he had pleaſed to have read on to</hi> Phil. 4.2. <hi>he would have found</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to ſignifie una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity; and St.</hi> Paul, 1 Cor. 12.25. <hi>oppoſes the</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>th t there be no ſchiſm in the body, but that all the members ſhould take care of</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>one for another; and therefore the</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>is very aptly uſed againſt ſchiſms and diviſions:</hi> and adds, <hi>I ſhould think that</hi> St. Chryſoſtom, Theodoret, <hi>and</hi> Theophilact, <hi>all underſtood the importance of a</hi> Greek <hi>phraſe, as well as our Author, and they all make no ſcruple to interpret it of the peace and concord of Chriſtians. And although</hi> Auſtin <hi>did not underſtand much</hi> Greek, <hi>yet he knew the general ſenſe of the Chriſtian Church about this place, and he par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly applies it to the peace of the Church in St</hi> Cyprian<hi>'s caſe.</hi>
               <q rend="margQuotes">By this taſt now (ſays the Dr.) let any man judg of the depth of this man's Learning, or rather the height of his confidence, who dares to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll the world, that the Univerſal ſtream and current of all Expoſitors is againſt my ſenſe of this Text; and for this uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal ſtream (beſides <hi>Grotius</hi>) who ſpeaks exactly to the ſame ſenſe with mine, quotes only <hi>Tirinus</hi> and <hi>Zanchy,</hi> and then cries, in a word they all conſpire againſt my interpretation.</q> And with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a few lines he adds, <q rend="margQuotes">But had it not been fairer dealing, in one word to have referred us to Mr. <hi>Pool</hi>'s <hi>Synopſis;</hi> for if he had looked into <hi>Zanchy</hi> himſelf, he would have found how ſharply he applied it againſt Diſſenters in the Church.</q>
            </p>
            <p>And in p. 203. after he had made him Advocate-General for Schiſmaticks, by an Oration put into his mouth, and pronounced be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore St. <hi>Auſtin, Cyprian,</hi> and other great oppoſers of Schiſm, thus he ſpeaks, <hi>Judg now, Reader, whether the Cauſes of the preſent Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, as they are laid down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y my Adverſary, do not equally defend the</hi> Donatills <hi>in their Schiſm; and his making ſo light of Schiſm, doth not give encouragement to men to make more. But I ſhall not ſend him ſo far back as</hi> Auſtin <hi>and</hi> Cyprian <hi>for better inſtruction in this matter; but I ſhall ſend him to one whoſe Writings he is better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with, even Mr.</hi> Baxter.</p>
            <p>And in page 304 the Dr. compares him with <hi>Andrelinus,</hi> of whom <hi>Eraſmus</hi> ſays, <q rend="margQuotes">That he was a good Poet, but his Verſes
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:105585:12"/>wanted one ſyllable, and that was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in <hi>Engliſh</hi> brains;</q> and this becauſe Mr. <hi>A.</hi> had ſaid, <hi>That National Churches deſtroy the being of other Churches under them; which</hi> (ſays the Dr.) <hi>I utterly deny; and there wants nothing but proof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To all this I ſhall reply as followeth: If Mr. <hi>A.</hi> do intermix any pleaſantneſs in his diſcourſe, 'tis preſently condemned as trifling, and he compared with Carmen and Porters. If he give his Readers any divertiſement, by intermingling ſome Wit and Fancy with his Reaſonings, he is ſcurrilous, and compared to <hi>Martin</hi> (an Author I confeſs that I never had the misfortune to read; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently famed for railing). If he interſperſe a little ſaltneſs among his Ratiocinations, he is ungentile, and a Buffoon, which is the Title wherewith a Gentleman hath lately graced him in a Reply to his Book. What ſhall Mr. <hi>A.</hi> do in this caſe? and how ſhall he pleaſe theſe Gentlemen? Would they have him turn fool to humour them, and lay aſide his Wit (which makes his Writings the more ſavoury and grateful) to do them a pleaſure? I do not find that thoſe that have replied to him, have laid any obligation upon him to do them ſuch a kindneſs; and I think he will be loath to purchaſe their favour and good will at ſo dear a rate.</p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>A.</hi> hath interpreted the <hi>Greek</hi> Phraſes, before mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, otherwiſe than <hi>Chryſoſtome, Theodoret, Theoplylact,</hi> and St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin:</hi> and what then! is he the only perſon that hath interpreted Texts of Scripture, contrary to the opinion and judgments of thoſe Fathers? do not all Expoſitors almoſt do the ſame? do not the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts (though otherwiſe obliged by the Decrees of the Council of <hi>Trent</hi>) do it? does not the admired <hi>Hugo Grotius</hi> do it? and I dare ſay, this excellent Dr. himſelf underſtands very many Texts of Scripture in other ſenſes than the ancient Fathers did expound them. Whether Mr <hi>A.</hi> have rightly interpreted the Texts in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie, I will not determine; but this I will ſay, he may be a Learned man, though he may have expounded them otherwiſe than St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> St. <hi>Theodoret,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Whether the univerſal current of all Expoſitors be againſt the Dr's ſenſe of his Text, as Mr. <hi>A.</hi> affirms, I know not (for my Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary is not furniſhed with all the Commentators in the world) nor will I ſay, that Mr. <hi>A.</hi> did look into <hi>lanchy</hi> himſelf, and not tranſcribe what he quotes from Mr. <hi>Pooles Synopſis;</hi> but this I think I may ſay, that I ſee no convincing evidence that Mr. <hi>A.</hi> did not peruſe that Author himſelf, and tranſcribe the words from
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105585:13"/>him, and not from Mr. <hi>Pool;</hi> and therefore I humbly conceive the Dr. hath affirmed, or at leaſt inſinuated more than he hath proved, <hi>viz.</hi> that Mr. <hi>A</hi>'s quotations are tranſcribed from the <hi>Synopſis Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticorum,</hi> and not from the Authors themſelves. But if Mr. <hi>A.</hi> muſt be a Pigmy in Learning, what honour is it then for the very great and learned Dr. to beat and overcome him?</p>
            <p>Let it be granted therefore for once, that Mr. <hi>A.</hi> is not the moſt learned or beſt-read man in the world, and that there are ſome, yea many that have learned and read much more than he; but what then? he may be a Maſter of Reaſon, and a man of ſome tolerable judgment, not withſtanding thoſe defects (or elſe many great men, and ſome that are in great reputation for wiſdom, muſt be num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred among Dolts, and ſit in the Claſſis of Fools) he may be able to underſtand the ſenſe of a Text of Scripture, and the dependance and connexion of it with the precedent and conſequent Verſes, and the ſcope and deſign of the Author therein. Theſe things may be done by men of competent underſtanding (and I think that will be granted to Mr. <hi>A.</hi>) though they never read all the Books in the <hi>Bodleian</hi> Library, or in ſome that are more meanly furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and 'tis ſome mens opinion, that the greateſt Readers are not always the moſt judicious men; and that if ſome very worthy men had read leſs, they might have underſtood more. Hence I think I may infer, that though Mr. <hi>A.</hi> ſhould not have read St. <hi>Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, &amp;c.</hi> nor many modern Commentators, yet he may be ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of expounding a Text of Scripture with the probability of truth, as well as thoſe that have read them all.</p>
            <p>And whereas it hath pleaſed the Learned Dr. to entitle him Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocate-General for Schiſmaticks, I am not ſatisfied that Mr. <hi>A.</hi> hath given any juſt reaſon for it. 'Tis true he hath ſaid, that ſome little and petty inconveniences ariſing from the levity and volubility of mers minds, is more eligible than the enſlaving mens judgments and conſciences, and ſurrendring their reaſon to naked will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, even as 'tis better to have a rational ſoul, though ſubject to miſtakes, than the ſoul of a brute which may be managed with a ſtrong bit and bridle, as you pleaſe. This is the ſenſe of Mr. <hi>A</hi>'s words in his Preface; and what hurt is there in them? Do not all Proteſtants ſpeak the ſame language? And is it not better that men e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r in ſome things, than that they put out their eyes, and ſee with thoſe of other men, blindly following their conduct, and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting and aſſenting to all their Impoſitions?</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:105585:13"/>
            <p>But the Dr. will ſay, Is Separation by reaſon of the levity of mens minds only, a ſmall or petty inconvenience? In anſwer whereunto, I would diſtinguiſh of Separation. There is a Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that proceeds upon reaſons apparently true, and ſuch is the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paration of Proteſtants from the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> and this is a great and neceſſary duty: There is a Separation that proceeds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on probable reaſons, which ſometimes are not cogent nor conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, and yet they may be ſuch as honeſt and upright minded men may not be able to free themſelves from being entangled and fetter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by them. This is an inconvenience, and whether it be great or ſmall, I know not how 'twill be avoided in this ſtate of weakneſs and imperfection, but by remedies worſe than the diſeaſe. But that which to my apprehenſion ſeems the beſt way of avoiding it is, Let nothing be made neceſſary to Communion in Churches, but a few plain neceſſary things, and this would certainly put an end to the moſt of thoſe Diviſions and Separations that have, and do vex the Chriſtian Churches, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> eſpecially and particularly: But there is a Separation that proceeds upon reaſons apparently falſe; ſuch is the Separation of the <hi>Socinians</hi> from the Reformed Churches, and ſuch is the Separation of many in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> This is intollerable, and by all prudent and Chriſtian means and endeavours to be repreſſed. By Separati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on here, I mean not barely refuſing <hi>Communion,</hi> but ſetting up new Churches in oppoſition to thoſe they have forſaken.</p>
            <p>But it may be enquired further, Whether Separation upon pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable, weak, and unconcluding reaſons, be not ſinful? I anſwer, Yes: but what if it be? there is ſome difference in ſins, as moſt men believe, and I ſee no great reaſon to doubt of it; and 'tis my opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that neither all Sinners, nor all Schiſmaticks, that are truly ſuch, muſt be ſent to the Mines, or to the Galleys. In brief, God will make a difference between Sinners at the day of Judgment; and I do believe, that the Governours of Churches, both Civil and Eccleſiaſtical, ſhould make ſome difference between them here. In the mean time, I would not be thought either to excuſe, or encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage unjuſtifiable Separations. I would that the ſinfulneſs of ſuch Separation ſhould be laid open with all its juſt aggravations, and that all juſt means be uſed by the Miniſters of the Goſpel, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent and hinder it, yea, and ſomething by the Magiſtrate too; but if Separation cannot be prevented (I mean ſuch as proceeds up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>probable,</hi> but not <hi>concluding</hi> reaſons) by thoſe endeavours, it
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105585:14"/>muſt be endured, an inconvenience being more eligible than a miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; and many things are, and muſt be ſuffered in all ſocieties, that are not, nor ought not to be approved. Such was divorce in the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Commonwealth, and ſome things elſe in that, and other ſocieties of men.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> doth not impoſe any thing upon its members by meer authority, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth, nor doth it force them to reſign their reaſon to naked will and pleaſure, nor command belief of thoſe notorious falſhoods which that imperious and Apoſtate Synagogue of Satan doth. I anſwer, 'tis readily granted (and we bleſs God for it), that this Church doth impoſe nothing that is apparently and groſly falſe; it commands no Idolatrous Worſhip, no opinions contrary to the common ſenſe of mankind, no invocation of Saints, Prayers for the dead, no Pilgrimages to Shrines, no ridiculous or ſottiſh Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions: but though it impoſe nothing groſly falſe, fooliſh or Superſtitious, yet ſome men think (and I know not how to confute them), that it impoſes ſome things dubious, uncertain, and unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, from which the Clergy cannot diſſent, but thereby they ſhut them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out of their office, and become uncapable of exerciſing their Miniſtry with the countenance and protection of the Laws. And if the Laity doubt the truth of any of its Impoſitions, and do pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh their doubts, and will be pertinacious in the defence of them, they are liable to excommunication, and all that is conſequent unto it: and in theſe things this Church is peremptory, and admits of no indulgence; Subſcribe, or Preach not the Goſpel; ſpeak nothing to the diſparagement of any thing in the Doctrine, Diſcipline, or Liturgy, or you ſhall be excommunicated, and given up to the Devil. Thus it ſpeaks, and this is its Language.</p>
            <p>I do eaſily grant, that this Church pretends not to Infallibility, as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> doth; but in whatſoever it determines, it avows it ſelf not miſtaken or deceived: And what is the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in effect, between a Church that aſſumes to it ſelf the title and approbation of Infallible, and a Church that ſays, I am not miſtaken in my Determinations and Impoſitions? Suppoſe two perſons, one a <hi>Neſtorian,</hi> the other an <hi>Eutichian;</hi> the one propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes in certain Articles, his Doctrine, ſo as confounds Chriſts <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,</hi> and withal tells you, he is Infallible, and you muſt ſubſcribe to, and acknowledg the truth of it, or prepare your ſelf for the Axe or the Gallows: the other propoſes his Doctrine, ſo as he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105585:14"/>divides Chriſts <hi>Perſon,</hi> but pretends not to be Infallible, but ſays, his Doctrine is true, and he is not miſtaken in it, and 'tis at your pleaſure, and in your choice either to ſubſcribe it, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare your ſelf for the Mines of <hi>Peru</hi> and the <hi>Indies.</hi> The Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication is obvious, and every one can make it without my manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction, or direction.</p>
            <p>But let me not be ſaid to defame this Church. I have ſaid al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready, that it impoſes nothing groſly and apparently falſe, but only ſome things unneceſſary, and uncertain. I will add here, the penalties impoſed upon thoſe that refuſe to own, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg, or do defame its determinations, are not ſo ſevere, nor ſanguinary, as in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, nor peradventure ſo certainly and ſeverely executed; but whether the peremptory impoſing things doubtful, controverted, uſeleſs, and unneceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, upon the legal and eſtabliſhed penalties, be not tyrannical and imperious, would deſerve a little conſideration. Why muſt all Miniſters be obliged to ſubſcribe to all things in the 39. Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Liturgy, and Book of Ordination, as containing nothing contrary to the Word of God? Why muſt they ſubſcribe the 20th Article, concerning the power of the Church to or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain Rites and Ceremonies? Why muſt they aſſent to the 8th Article, where 'tis ſaid, that the <hi>Athanaſian</hi> Creed ought throughly to be received and believed? why muſt the ſalvation of Infants being baptized, and dying before the commiſſion of actual ſin, be acknowledged as certain by the Word of God? and why muſt they aſſent to, and ſubſcribe the lawfulneſs of the uſe of the Croſs in Baptiſm, with more that might be menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned? Are theſe things certain, and ſo clear and obvious, that an honeſt man can't doubt of them? Are theſe things neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry? Cannot a man be a Miniſter, or a Chriſtian that doth not, nor cannot believe them? This cannot, or at leaſt ought not to be imagined or affirmed; why then doth the Church of <hi>England</hi> require Miniſters to ſubſcribe unto them? and why muſt none of the Laity diſpute the truth of them? What rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon can be alledged for it, but its own good will and pleaſure? I know no other that can be given of it, thither it muſt be referred at laſt. And whether this be not to exerciſe an Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire over the judgments and conſciences of men, and to command the ſurrender of their reaſon to naked will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I leave to conſideration. It hath the likeneſs and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105585:15"/>of it; and how the Church of <hi>England</hi> will fairly free themſelves of it, I do not yet diſcern; I would be glad to ſee it done; for the exerciſe of Empire over the conſciences of men in uncertain and unneceſſary things, is a very evil and miſchievous thing, an Engine of the Devil, by which I do believe he hath done more miſchief in the Church of God, than by all the Heathen perſecutions; and I know no end is ſerved by it, unleſs it be to choak conſcientious men; for all men of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience are not Latitudinarians, nor like to be in my apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>The ſum of what I have ſaid in theſe three laſt Paragraphs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is this; Mr. <hi>A.</hi> hath ſaid, ſome little and petty inconveniencies ariſing from the levity and inconſtancy of mens minds, is more eligible than the proſtituting mens conſciences, and reſigning them to the naked wills of men, which is no more than moſt Proteſtants have ſaid before him.</p>
            <p>Separations are various; ſome proceed upon reaſons apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly true, and theſe are a neceſſary duty; ſome proceed upon reaſons apparently falſe, and theſe are greatly ſinful and intol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable; others proceed upon probable reaſons, which though ſpecious and fair, yet are not concluding, theſe are not without ſin, yet muſt be endured, an inconvenience being better than a miſchief: And this, I conceive is the ſeparation which the Dr. ſays. Mr. <hi>A.</hi> makes very light of, which yet I do not beileve, unleſs it be comparatively, and for the ſake of which I do not think him worthy of the appellation of Advocate-general for Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks.</p>
            <p>The Church of <hi>England</hi> doth not pretend to be infallible, but is as peremptory in its determinations as if it were. It impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes nothing groſly falſe, and againſt common ſenſe and reaſon, but it requires things unneceſſary and uncertain, with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yielding rigour, and this looks like tyranny; and if the Church of <hi>England</hi> think it ſelf defamed by that inſinuation, it may vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate it ſelf if it can.</p>
            <p>To the Drs. inſinuation, that Mr. <hi>A</hi> is not much acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Writings of <hi>Cyprian</hi> and St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and that he hath been more converſant in thoſe of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> I might en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire where is the Proof? and what evidence doth this Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man produce for the confirmation of it? I have looked his Book all over, but I can find none, nor do I imagine what
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105585:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>hath given occaſion to the Dr. to think ſo: 'tis true Mr. <hi>A</hi> doth not quote thoſe Fathers in his Book; but doth it follow from thence, that he never read them? There are many Books which the Excellent Dr. himſelf hath never quoted in any of his writings; but he that ſhould infer from thence, that he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver read them, would certainly injure and traduce him, But Mr. <hi>A.</hi> is a Diſſenter, and peradventure for that reaſon muſt be an unlearned and unread man, whoſe reaſon muſt be as weak therefore as his reading is ſmall, and there muſt be no more ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument in his diſcourſe, than there was of Wit or Brains in <hi>Andrelinus</hi> his Poems; which, to ſpeak modeſtly, is a ſcurrilous compariſon, and not becoming the Pen of the Reverend Dr.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>B.</hi> had ſaid ſomething in his Anſwer to the Drs. Sermon, of the Peoples Power, or right of chooſing, or at leaſt conſenting to the choice of their own Paſtors; whereupon he ſays, that <hi>Mr.</hi> B. <hi>is very tragical upon this argument, and keeps not within tollera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble bounds of diſcretion, in pleading the Peoples Right or Cauſe againſt Magiſtrates, Patrons and Laws,</hi> p. 307. And p. 329. he ſays, <hi>Mr.</hi> B. <hi>is unſatisfied with any Laws that are made in this matter:</hi> and in the ſame page he ſays, <hi>that one would think by Mr.</hi> B<hi>'s Doctrine, all Laws about Patronage are void in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; and all Rights of Advouſon in the King, Noblemen, Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen, and the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities, are meer uſurpations, and things utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unlawful among Chriſtians, ſince he makes ſuch a perſonal ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to chooſe their own Paſtors, to lie on the People, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not transfer it by their own Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I reply, Mr. <hi>B.</hi> will be well enough ſatisfied, if the People may have the liberty of conſenting to the Paſtor that by the Patron is preſented to them; and what is there of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableneſs in ſuch a deſign or propoſal? Bleſſed be God there are in <hi>England</hi> many worthy Gentlemen that take care of the diſpoſal of their Livings, and preſent ſober and learned men unto them; and in my obſervation, ſuch perſons are uſually ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable to the People, and they conſent to them without objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or oppoſition; but then it muſt be acknowledged, that there are many others that take no care of the diſpoſal of them, ſome are Papiſts, and give their Livings to the nomination of their Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, and they ſell them to whomſoever will give moſt for them; others are prophane Senſualiſts, and ſuch men will preſent vitious, debauched perſons. Piety and a ſober Converſation may preclude,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:105585:16"/>but will never commend a man to their preſentation. And what if for theſe reaſons, and more that might be mentioned, the people had a conſenting power permitted to them? are the Rights of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tronage invaded or abdicated, injured or deſtroyed thereby? Hath not the Biſhop power in ſome caſes to refuſe the Clerk that is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to him for inſtitution? and is the Patrons right evacuated by it? Surely no, I never heard any ſuch thing affirmed, or pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended; and if the Patrons right may be preſerved with a power of juſt and reaſonable diſſent and conſent in the Biſhop, it may be alſo preſerved with the ſame power in the people: Are not Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons right preſerved, unleſs they may impoſe upon the people ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant and ſcandalous Miniſters, that are neither able nor willing to Preach the Doctrines of Faith and Godlineſs? are not their rights preſerved unleſs they have the liberty of preſenting whom they liſt, and ſending them ſuch Preachers, as inſtead of being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples to the flock in Piety, Juſtice, Charity, and Sobriety, ſhall be enſamples of Impiety, Cruelty, Injuſtice, and Intemperance un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them?</p>
            <p>If it ſhould be ſaid, that ſuch cannot procure Orders, nor Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution from the Dioceſan: I anſwer, 'tis in vain to diſpute againſt ſenſe and experience; and men will never believe that cannot be done which they ſee done before their eyes; and the Biſhops are cheated by Certificates and Teſtimonials, for there are few men ſo bad, that cannot find others as bad as themſelves, to vouch for them.</p>
            <p>And if this liberty were granted to the people, I am not appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive of thoſe evil conſequences that the Dr. ſeems to fear, who tells us, <hi>Where a Pariſh is divided in their opinions about Religion (as we know too many are at this day) all the ſeveral parties,</hi> Anabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts, Quakers, <hi>yea and</hi> Papiſts, <hi>as well as others, will put in for a ſhare in what concerns their ſouls, and conſequently chuſe a Paſtor each party to themſelves, and the Incumbent that is legally intitled to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of the Living, may poſſeſs them, and the people may follow the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of other Guides, even ſuch as themſelves have choſen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For I would propoſe that this Liberty might be legally granted to the people, and that their conſent and diſſent ſhould be limited by juſt Rules, and upon equitable Reaſons, and that our Superiors might ſuperintend them in the exerciſe of it, and ſee that they do not abuſe it. For ſurely there is ſome difference between the uſe of Power<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Liberty, and Priviledg, and the abuſe of it; and one may
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105585:16"/>be reſtrained, without taking away the other. The abuſe of the peoples liberty in the choice of a <hi>Quaker</hi> or <hi>Socinian,</hi> or a <hi>Papiſt</hi> for their Teacher, may be reſtrained without depriving them of the liberty of refuſing a wicked, ſcandalous, ignorant wretch, or chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an honeſt, pious, learned, and ſober man. Cannot the Learned Dr. reſtrain his Daughter from chuſing a prophane Senſualiſt (whoſe God is his belly, and hath nothing brave or generous in his ſoul) or her Husband, without depriving her of the liverty of chuſing a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> honeſt, worthy, brave, and virtuous man? And this I think is all that Mr. <hi>B.</hi> deſires, at leaſt this would ſatisfie him; and I know not why the Learned Dr. repreſents this opinion or deſire of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> in ſo monſtrous and odious a manner, unleſs it be to make him an offence to Noblemen, Gentlemen, Univerſities, and all ſuch as have right of Patronage belonging to them.</p>
            <p>Page 371. <hi>The Author of the Letter out of the Countrey</hi> (ſays the Dr.) <hi>lays the foundation of the Separation upon the force of ſcruples, mighty ſcruples, ſcruples of a long ſtanding, and of a large extent; ſcruples that there is no hopes to remove, without ſome very o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verpowering impreſſions on mens minds.</hi> To which the Dr. replies, <hi>I am ſo much of another mind, that I think a little impartiality, and due conſideration, would do the buſineſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I cannot be ſo uncharitable as to believe, that none of the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenters do impartially conſider the things in controverſie between them and the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and which are the grounds of the preſent Separation, when they do ſolemnly profeſs the contrary, with appeals to God who ſearcheth the hearts, and trieth the reins; and 'tis ſevere to give them the lye in ſuch a caſe, where 'tis certain we are no competent or capable judges. But ſuppoſe they (at leaſt ſome of them) ſhould not impartially conſider (and 'tis no eaſie matter either for Conſenters or Diſſenters to lay aſide all partiali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty) what will be inferred from thence? Muſt they not be endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red upon the earth? Are they inſufferable in the Land? If all were baniſhed, impriſoned, or hanged, that are guilty of no greater ſins than a little partiality in conſideration, there would be few <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts</hi> or <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> left in this Nation. But peradventure it may be no great fault to be partial in the conſideration of other things, when to be partial in conſidering the grounds and reaſons of the preſent Separation, is an unpardonable ſin, and not to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105585:17"/>in this world, whatever it may be in the world to come.</p>
            <p>Though the Dr. ſeems to think it a thing of no great difficulty to cure mens ſcruples, in the words above-mentioned, and in ſome others in the following page; yet he ſpeaks to a contrary ſenſe, p. 48. of his Preface, where he tells us of <hi>the almoſt invincible igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of ſome weaker people, and the uncurable biaſs of ſome mens minds.</hi> Is the almoſt invincible ignorance of weak people eaſily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved? yes, faith the Dr. <hi>Honeſt men may be cured of their errors and miſtakes.</hi> But how is it to be done? <hi>why, by bringing them to a better temper, and to more judgment,</hi> p. 372. I thought ſo; but how ſhall we do that? Are the almoſt invincibly ignorant, made judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous upon eaſie endeavours? And are thoſe that have incurable byaſſes upon their minds, brought to a better temper of mind with a wet finger? I know not what the Drs. experience is, but I am ſure 'tis otherwiſe in mine, and in many others. I find it impoſſible to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the ignorance, and take off the prejudices and byaſſes of ſome peoples minds, humanely ſpeaking, as the phraſe now is; and the reaſon is obvious, I can bring them light, but I cannot give them eyes. I can propound reaſon and evidence ſufficient, as I think, to remove their fears, ſcruples, and prejudices; but I cannot give them underſtandings to apprehend and perceive the cogency, weight and ſufficiency thereof. Mens underſtandings are of as many differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing degrees and ſizes, as their faces are of differing ſhapes and fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; and what one man can perceive and underſtand, another can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not do. One man can ſee the ſmalleſt needles or hairs, another can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſee them, though it were to ſave his life. Beſides, there are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiarities in the underſtandings of men; how they came there, I will neither enquire nor determine; but that there are ſuch things, cannot be denied. The Doctrine of <hi>Calvin</hi> in the five points, to ſome men ſeems utterly irrational, and contrary to the common ſentiments of mankind, and all that they read and hear for the alteration of their apprehenſions, makes no impreſſion or change up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. Others there are that have the ſame apprehenſions of the Doctrine of <hi>Arminius</hi> in thoſe points; and the like I might ſay of many other Controverſies in Religion. Mens minds ſeem inclined to embrace one part of the Controverſie, by a peculiarity of frame, temper, and diſpoſition; and in this caſe 'tis a mighty difficulty to prevail with ſuch men to alter their apprehenſions, if not impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. Which things being premiſed, and certain, I think not thoſe words of Mr. <hi>B.</hi> ſo ſevere as the Dr. ſeems to imagine them, <hi>viz.</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:105585:17"/>That <hi>he that thinks his own or others Reaſonings will ever change all the truly honeſt Chriſtians in the Land (as to the unlawfulneſs of the things impoſed) knoweth ſo little of matters, or of men, or of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that he is unmeet to be a Biſhop or Prieſt:</hi> for is not he fit for that Office, or thoſe Employments, that doth not know, that the meaſures and degrees of mens underſtandings are almoſt infinite; and that they will never agree, unleſs it be in a few plain, great, and neceſſary things, and that in multitudes of leſſer things they will diſſert for ever; and that in this diverſity of underſtandings 'tis impoſſible it ſhould be otherwiſe; and that under this diverſity of apprehenſions, there will be ſome diverſity of practiſes too, where men fear God, and have a value for their own Conſciences. and the ſuggeſtions thereof? is he fit to bear the Office of a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop, or a Prieſt, that is ignorant of theſe things? ſurely he is very little acquainted in the great variety and imperfections of humane minds, that thinks, that all Chriſtians will ever be of one mind in many leſſer things: and he is as little acquainted with the Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of men, that thinks honeſt Chriſtians will be of the ſame practice, where their judgments are ſo much divided. I will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this Paragraph with the following Story, which will ſerve to evince the incurableneſs of ſome peoples jealouſies and ſcruples; and I'le do it in the words of the perſon that ſent it to me. <hi>I know a Gentlewoman whoſe Parents were of the Congregational perſuaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſuch was her education; n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vertheleſs after her marriage (her husband being conformable) ſhe accompanied him to the publick worſhip of God, and this ſhe did for ſome years; but all this time her ſcruples, and her fears, and the jealouſies of her Conſcience did ſo plague and torment her, that ſhe had little or no comfort in her life, yea, he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bodily health was very much weakned, and impaired by the perturbations of her mind: this having been her condition for ſome years, at length ſhe forſook the publick and eſtabliſhed worſhip, betook her ſelf to a Congregational Church, and now lives in peace, and tollerable heath. The Gentlewoman, I do believe, is truly pious and conſcienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and doth avow, that could ſhe be ſatisfied of the lawfulneſs of attending on the publick way of worſhip, ſhe would do it with all her heart. Her reaſon and arguments may be eaſily anſwered, and ſhe may be ſilenced, and, one would think, her judgment ſatisfied; but her ſcruples return again like a Torrent, and ſhe cannot reſiſt them;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:105585:18"/>and, in plain</hi> Engliſh, <hi>are incurable, without ſome very great and transforming impreſſions from above. And this is no rare or ſingle caſe, but what often occurs, as thoſe men know that converſe with the conſciences of Chriſtians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Dr. returns again to the Author of the Letter out of the Countrey, <hi>pag.</hi> 376. and thus he ſpeaks concerning him, <hi>The main force of what he ſaith</hi> (i.e. <hi>the Author of that Letter</hi>) <hi>lyes in this, that thoſe that cannot conquer thier ſcruples as to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with our Church, muſt either return to the ſtate of Paganiſm, or ſet up new Churches, by joining with the ejected Miniſters.</hi> To which the Dr. replies, <hi>This is new Doctrine, and never heard of in the days of the old Puritans; for they ſuppoſed men obliged to continue in the communion of this Church, although there were ſome things they ſcrupled, and could not conquer thoſe ſcruples; and this they ſuppoſed to be far enough from Paganiſm.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The old Puritans did ſuppoſe, that thoſe that ſcrupled <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſterial</hi> communion, were obliged to continue as Lay-men in the communion of this Church: But what is this to thoſe that ſcruple <hi>Lay</hi>-commuion, which is the caſe of many now in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land?</hi> And what ſhall theſe people do? they muſt either com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate againſt their Conſciences, or joyn with the ejected Miniſters, or live as <hi>Pagans;</hi> and which it is the Dr. will ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe them to, I cannot tell; but 'tis poſſible we may know here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. If he ſhould ſay, they muſt put off their ſcruples, and communicate with the licenſe and approbation of their conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences; I ſay ſo too. 'Tis their duty to endeavour it: but what if after all the endeavours they can uſe, they cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entangle their minds from them, what ſhall they do then? I beſeech the Learned Dr. to give ſome directions to theſe ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous perſons in this caſe.</p>
            <p>In the ſame Page the Dr. deſires to know, <hi>whether as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as men do ſcruple joyning with others, their ſeparation be lawful?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:105585:18"/>
            <p>And I do deſire to know, whether all unlawful ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be intollerable? and whether all Schiſmaticks, that are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo, muſt be impriſoned, ruined and undone, or ſent to <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſus,</hi> and the <hi>Caſpian</hi> Mountains? When the Dr. hath an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered this enquiry, peradventure he may receive and Anſwer to the other, if he cannot anſwer it himſelf.</p>
            <p>The D. adds in the ſame, and the following Page, <hi>If it be lawful to ſeparate as often as men ſcruple the lawfulneſs of joyning in communion with out Church, 'tis in vain to talk of any ſetled Conſtitution, whether Epiſcopal, Presbyterian, or Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent; for this Principle overthrows them all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To which I anſwer, I do not think it lawful to ſeparate as often as men ſcruple joyning in communion; yet I do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve it lawful to tolerate ſome unlawful ſeparations, yea and neceſſary too; but let no unneceſſary occaſions of ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and ſeparation be given. Let no ſeparations for the ſake of undoubted truths, and the great eſſentials, of Faith and Godlineſs be allowed. Let the Congregations in the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be furniſhed with pious and holy Miniſters, and ſome diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline exerciſed in them, and 'twill be found that the number of Separatiſts will not be great, and a ſtop will be put to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs and encreaſe of them, and a few years will reduce them almoſt to none: for if the Cauſes of Separation be looked in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, they will be found to be the impoſing and requiring of unneceſſary and doubtful things, ignorant and ſcandalous Preachers, and undiſciplined Churches. Whether theſe things will <hi>juſtifie</hi> it, I will not ſay; but that they are the main <hi>Cauſes</hi> of it, cannot be denied by any conſidering man. And if theſe be not removed, Separation will be continued, unleſs the Popiſh method of Cure be undertaken, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Fire and Faggot, Racks and Tortures, Confiſcations and Puniſhments, which certainly are Remedies that were never taught by Chriſt Jeſus, the Lover and Saviour of mankind; but by the Devil, the great enemy, hater and deſtroyer of them.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:105585:19"/>
            <p>And let me add further, that I ſee no reaſon to infer, that tolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Separation upon tolerable ſcruples, will deſtroy all Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment in the Church: for I think there was a Government in the Church, when the <hi>Novatians</hi> were tolerated both at <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> for ſome hundreds of years, as the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor very well knows; and I hope we have a Government in the Nation, though ſome men tranſgreſs the eſtabliſhed Laws thereof, yea and are permitted ſo to do with impunity. Yet I would diſtinguiſh between Separation in the bud and bloſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and Separation ripe and grown, as 'tis with us in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> and I would ſay, that ſome things may be done, and ſome ſeverities uſed to cruſh and prevent the encreaſe of it when budding; which may not be done to extinguiſh and root it out when its grown and encreaſed, and the number of thoſe that ſeparate, is very great and numerous. Some few ſingle Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks (not that are made ſuch by unneceſſary Impoſitions, but ſuch as make themſelves ſuch by unreaſonable and unwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable ſcruples and objections) may after the uſe of admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, teaching, and inſtruction, and a patient waiting for the ſucceſs of them, be treated with ſome rigor and moderate harſhneſs. But thouſands and ten thouſands are too many ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be laid in Gaols, or ſent to the barren deſerts of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rabia,</hi> or other Countreys at leſſer diſtance from us.</p>
            <p>Page 378. The Learned Dr. wonders that <hi>none of thoſe who have undertaken to defend the cauſe of Separation, have taken any care to put ſtop to it, or to let us know where we may fix and ſee an end of it: which ſcruples are to be allowed, and what not; and whether it be lawful to ſeparate, as long as men can go on in ſcruples, and ſay they cannot conquer them</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>B</hi> I ſuppoſe, is one of them which the Doctor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves hath undertaken to defend the cauſe of Separation; and I wonder the Doctor ſhould not obſerve that he hath taken care to put a ſtop to it, and let us know what ſcruples are to be allowed, and what not. Hath he not ſaid over and, over,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:105585:19"/>even to times without number, That a difference is to be made betwixt <hi>tolerable</hi> and <hi>intolerable</hi> ſcruples and errors; betwixt ſcruples that may be defended by probable reaſons, and ſuch as have nothing to be pleaded on their behalf, but apparent and obvious falſhoods; betwixt ſcruples about unneceſſary and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putable things, and ſuch as are about neceſſary and undoubted truths, and ſo owned and confeſſed by all Chriſtians? and in ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this, he hath told us what ſcruples are to be allowed, and what not; and where to put a ſtop to Separation. 'Tis true theſe are but general rules to direct us by, in judging of allowable and unallowable errors and ſcruples, and where and when to put a ſtop to Separations; but the application of them to particular caſes, is not difficult; and ſince errors and ſcruples are infinite, I hope the Dr. will not, nor doth not expect that Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> ſhould name all particularly that are tolerable and intolerable; this were to ſet him and Employment that might laſt to the worlds end, if he could live ſo long, and would prevent his writing of Books to the offence of his Conformable brethren; but, I think, would pleaſe many of them very well, who are willing to be rid of him and his Books.</p>
            <p>But Sir, I have, in obedience to your commands, put my Sic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kle too far into other mens Harveſts; and therefore will here put a period to my <hi>Remarks.</hi> Beſides, I hear Mr. <hi>B.</hi> hath replied to the Learned Dr. and that his Book is abroad in the world, though I have not ſeen it as yet, living as you know, at a great diſtance, and in a ſmall Village that hath little commerce wit <hi>London.</hi> I know you will pardon all the faults and imperfections of theſe haſty Lines; and when you have read them, do what you pleaſe with them. I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>SIR,</salute> 
               <signed>Your very true Friend and Servant,</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
